### **RAHUL JAIN**

Hyderabad, Telangana **Phone no:** 090323-20120

Email: jain.rahul8888@gmail.com

#### **Career Vision**

To join an organization in which my hard work & sincerity will be utilized to grow along with organization.

#### **Professional Summary**

9.5+ years of total experience in industry which includes 6+ years of experience in Java Technologies, 3+ years of experience in Data analytics, NLP, Machine learning algorithms using python and Big Data technologies.

Expertise in improving the performance of various system in big data, ETL and ML technologies.

3+ yrs of experience in leading the development team.

Possess good knowledge of predictive analytics using supervised ML like Linear regression, Logistic regression, RF and KNN etc python.

Good knowledge of descriptive analytics and designing the business report.

Excellent in writing SQL queries for high level data understanding.

Good in understanding the business requirement and raw data. Good with performing data engineering for ML training and testing data samples.

Possess good Technical and Architectural knowledge of Big Data technologies such as Spark, MapReduce, HDFS, Pig, Hive, Sqoop.

Good knowledge of working on AWS and Google Cloud platform.

Good knowledge in real time data streaming analytics using kafka.

Good in understanding the business requirement and raw data. Good with performing data engineering for ML training and testing samples.

Excellent Java development skills using J2EE and web services.

Having B1/B2 US Visa, valid for 7 yrs.

Extensive experience in developing various web based applications using Spring and OAF.

Good experience in handling Use Cases, Functional Specification, Knowledge Transfers and Business Analysis.

#### **Professional Experience**

Currently working as Big Data Lead Developer for Cashe(Bhanix Finance Pvt. Ltd.), Hyderabad, Apr 2018- Till Date

Worked as Sr. Consultant for Deloitte Consulting India Pvt. ltd., Hyderabad, Jan 2017- March 2018 Worked as Associate Lead-Big Data Technologies for Atmecs Technologies Pvt. Ltd., Hyderabad, Nov 2015 - Jan 2017

Worked as a Project Lead for Oracle India Pvt Ltd., Hyderabad, June 2011 -Nov 2015

Worked as a Systems Engineer for Infosys Technologies Ltd., Hyderabad, Feb 2009 – June 2011

#### **Technical Skill Set**

Programming Languages	:	JAVA, J2EE, Python			
Machine Learning	:	Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, KNN, Random Forest, XGBoost.			
Big Data		Spark, HDFS, Kafka, MapReduce, Sqoop, Hive, Pig			
AWS/	:	S3, SQS, EMR, Redshift, Google Dataproc, Google BigQuery, Google			
Google Cloud Platform		storage, Google datalabs.			

Framework	:	OAF, Spring	
IDE Tools	: Jupyter Notebook, JDeveloper, Eclipse, SQL Developer		
Database		Oracle, MySQL,Cassandra, MongoDB	
Operating Systems		Window 7/10, Ubuntu	
Others : Mav		Maven, Git, Shell Script,	

#### **Achievements**

Received Award for Exceptional contribution for performance improvement of SLQ Score algorithm. Received Extra Mile Award for new enhancement in Field Service product of Oracle EBS family, In Oracle India Pvt Ltd.

Received On The Spot Award for my contribution in Web Service lap for PEAS, in Infosys Technologies Limited.

Sun Certified Java 1.6 programmer.

### **Projects Experience**

# Cashe(Online short term money lending App)

Apr 2018– Till Date

Description: Cashe is online short term money lending app with 2 million of downloads. We have developed two different ML model based for credit score for customers. First one called as GM score developed in using xgboost decision tree algorithm. It's supervised ML model which has to be retrained on monthly basis. The new form of ML code has been written called SLQ scores, which is semi supervised ML algorithm. This algo has its own implementations and works on real time data and calculates slq scores in between 1-2 min. of trigger point.

## Responsibilities:

SLQ model development, feature and performance improvisation.

SLQ etl and engine infrastructure and production issues.

Real time customer data analysis, customer sms data analysis using kafka.

Data cleaning and analysis for future improvisation.

Data migration from sql database to s3.

Role: Big data lead developer

Team Size: 30

Language and scripts: Java, MapReduce, Python, Kafka, Spark.

Other tools: AWS, MySQL

### User Interaction History(Deloitte-Google Client)

Jan 2017– March 2018

Description: As Google customer's database is huge and it's tough to identify the potential customers for sales marketing team. We have developed the data model for user interaction history across the products and SFDC source. This data model is used to prepare the input data for various analytical ML models for prediction and optimization problems. We do lot of engineering and data preparation for model improvisation.

## Responsibilities:

Leading development team, also gathering requirement from client, analyzing it and proposing the

solution.

Development of ML model for prediction of lead and contact conversion for marketing team.

Development of ML model for opportunity conversion for sales team.

Model testing and feature engineering for model optimization.

Present the solution prototype and accuracy metrics and plan to the client.

Review and Develop the queries on big query for extraction and transformation.

Technical and functional design document, runbook and code review.

Review the test cases and test data to get the accuracy of the solution.

Completely involved in the requirement analysis phase.

Role: Sr. Consultant

Team Size: 9

Language and scripts: Google SQL, Python, Pig, Datalabs, Spark.

Other tools: Google Big Query, Dataproc, Datalabs

## Eureka(Atmecs-Citrix Client)

NOV 2015– Jan 2017

Description: Client is Citrix Systems. Citrix want to move all their business data onto cloud based data warehouse. This data will be input to design any BI dashboard and reports. We are using sqoop as extraction tool. Mapreduce in java and pig scripts for transformation logic. Amazon S3 as a staging cloud storage. Mapr distribution cluster is being used to run the hadoop jobs. Final transformed data is transferred to redshift. Oozie is used to develop the workflow. So basically, This project needs extensive knowledge on number of technologies.

## Responsibilities:

Leading development team, also gathering requirement from client, analyzing it and proposing the solution.

Review and Develop MapReduce, Pig job for transformation logic.

Debugging the jobs on hadoop cluster.

Developed the Extraction framework to load data from rdbms depends on full, range and incremental load.

Technical and functional design document, runbook and code review.

Completely involved in the requirement analysis phase.

Troubleshoot mapreduce jobs, PIG scripts and JUnit test cases.

Role: Associate Lead-Big Data Technologies

Team Size: 15

Language and scripts: JAVA, Mapreduce, Pig, Spark Other tools: Eclipse, Sqoop, Git, Maven, HDFS, S3 Explorer

# Field Service & Spares Management product(Oracle)

**JUNE 2011 – NOV 2015** 

**Description**: Field service & spares management are product in customer support module of Oracle E-Business Suite R12.

Oracle Field Service drives profitability by automating the process of dispatching field technicians to service calls in remote locations. Field Service improves customer satisfaction by more accurately predicting a window to promise for service delivery, and it contains the Assignment Manager

designed to eliminate guesswork surrounding qualification, availability, and geographic relevance of each field service technician.

Oracle Spares Management helps reduce inventory costs by providing logistics and planning features that directly address the selection and delivery of spare parts to field locations. Oracle Spares Management includes return processing capabilities that ensure all parts are accounted for — enabling you to take advantage of warranty and return salvage values.

This product design needs the knowledge of JAVA, J2EE, OAF, AOL,XML, pl/sql and Unix.

## Responsibilities:

Created OAF UI from scratch based on functional documents.

Debugging issues in customer instances.

Developed Pig scripts to transform the data for analytics.

Completely involved in the requirement analysis phase.

Preparing analysis document for the existing code.

Created Technical design documents based on business process requirements.

Role: Project Lead Duration : 40 months

Team Size : 6 Framework : OAF

Language : JAVA, J2EE, Pig Other tools: Jdev, Oracle Forms

# PEAS-Process Execution, Analysis and Simulation(Infosys)

SEPT 2009 – JUNE 2011

Description: PEAS is a product for BPM (Business Process Management) which is used to execute Process workflow model in a failure safe manner.

PEAS uses BPML as its workflow model, which is generated using a process modeler, Influx. A business model can be created in Influx which is stored as BPML file. The PEAS engine reads and analyses to execute the activities in proper order. For fail safety it uses database as its store. It has the capacity to execute a process model, resume from a failure, automatic activity assignment, scheduled activities, etc. It is flexible enough to start multiple core engine integrated via the load balancer. This product design needs the knowledge of BPML, JAVA, Struts, Hibernate, XML parsing, web services, etc.

## Responsibilities:

Developed web based application using JSP and servlet and GWT.

Created workflows in Influx & executed in PEAS engine.

Created Installer for the PEAS using swings.

Performed Unit testing.

Prepared support documents for future help.

Role: Systems engineer Duration: 13 months

Team Size: 17

Tools Used: Influx, Eclipse

Language: Java, J2EE, Struts for portal.

Other: Ant build, soapUI

### **Educational Qualifications**

Examination	College/ School	Board/ University	Year	Marks(%)
B.E (Comp. Science)	M.I.T., Indore	R. G. P. V., Bhopal	2008	68.7 %
Higher Secondary	Takshshila H.S., Indore	M. P. B. S. E., Bhopal	2004	73.5 %
High School	Takshshila H.S., Indore	M. P. B. S. E., Bhopal	2002	65.4 %

## Trainings:

Attended training for hadoop development in various ecosystems.

Attended training to develop web based application using OA framework from scratch.

Attended training for pl/sql development.

Attended training for Inventory management in oracle apps.

### **Personal Life**

Date of Birth : 08th Aug. 1987

Marital status : Married Nationality : Indian

Visa : B1/B2(8 yrs) Languages spoken : English, Hindi

Date: (Rahul Jain)